Guide to the John Holtz papers ARCH126
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
John Holtz papers
1963-1990
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
Holtz, John
ARCH126
0.79 Linear Feet (5 containers)
This small collection consists of materials pertaining to the International Contemporary Organ Music Festival, and the career of John Holtz.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to all researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred to the University Archives and Special Collections from Allen Library. Based on the content, the collection is believed to have been originally created by John Holtz.
Biographical Note - John Cromwell Holtz
John Holtz was the founder and director of the International Contemporary Organ Music Festival from 1971-1984.[Source: "Holtz, John Cromwell," Hartford Courant, October 31, 2001.]
Scope and Contents
This collection consists primarily of printed music and scores, and in some cases synopses, texts, and instructions, and correspondence regarding organ compositions and performances. Many of these compositions were composed and/or performed for the International Contemporary Organ Music Festival. The collection also contains programs from Holtz's performances, scrapbooks and publicity materials of his career and the organ festival, as well as notes, writings, and other various papers.
Related Materials
Hartt School Collection (ARCH062), "International Contemporary Organ Music Festival" file.
Composition (Music); Composers; Organ music; Scores; Sheet music; Sound recordings; International Contemporary Organ Music Festival; Shackelford, Rudy, 1944-; Xenakis, Iannis, 1922-2001; Plush, Vincent, 1950-; Krenek, Ernst, 1900-1991; Hashagen, Klaus, 1924-1998
- Compositions, 1963-1982, undated; 9 Folders legal size; 1 Folders 20 x 24" oversize; 4 Folders 13 x 18" oversize (Box 1, Folder 1-9, Box Shared Oversized 2, Folder OV 1 (Gmeeoorh), Folder OV folder 3, Box Shared Small Oversized 2, Folder OV 4-7)
  Historical Note - Gmeeoorh
  Gmeeoorh was written in 1974 and was intended to premiere at the 1974 International Contemporary Organ Music Festival. However, it was cancelled due to lack of time to prepare (See Hartt School Collection (ARCH062), "International Contemporary Organ Music Festival" file for more details). Gmeeoorh premiered on February 24, 1975 at the South Church in New Britain and was performed by Clyde Holloway. Holloway later performed the piece again at the 1975 International Contemporary Organ Music Festival in June.
  Scope and Contents
  This files consists primarily of printed music and scores, and in some cases synopses, texts, and instructions, for the following: Organ Music by Felix Werder (1963, 1973); Gmeeoorh by Iannis Xenakis (1974); The Wound-Dresser, Melodrama, After Walt Whitman by Rudy Shakelford (Circa 1975- circa 1976); Chrysalis by Vincent Plush (1978); Opus 231 by Ernst Krenek (1900, printed with annotations 1979); Toccata I and Toccatta II by Klaus Hashagen (1979); Selections from the National Convention of the American Guild of Organists (from June 1982 Meeting); Sonata in Two Movements and Epilogue by Sven-Erik Back (1983); Toccata e Corale Boleslaw Woytowicz in Memoriam by Witold Szalonek (1988); Encompassing: for Two Organists by Vincent Plush (undated); and some unidentified organ music (undated).
  Many of these pieces were commissioned for the Institute of Contemporary Organ Music and/or dedicated to John Holtz.
- Programs, 1968-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
- Scrapbooks, 1971-1979; 2 Volumes (Box 1, Folder 13, Box Shared Oversized 2)
- Correspondence, 1980-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Notebook, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Writings, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Publicity, 1971-1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
- Hartt Class Exams, 1964-1986, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Vitae, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Sabbatical Reading Materials, 1971-1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Basically Baroque, 1982- Circa 1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Applied Area Chairpersons Meeting Minutes, 1990 Apr 2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Die Orgel von St. Sebald, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Recording of Glossolalia by Richard Felciano, 1967; 1 Reels audio reel 1/4 inch tape, 7 inch wide reel (Box 2)
  Consists of one audio reel of Felciano, Richard. Glossolalia: Electronic Tape for use with Baritone, Percussion, and Organ. Cincinnati, Ohio: World Library Publications, 1967.